All right, Matthew 18 and going 21 to
35.
Then Peter came up and said to him,
"Lord, how often will my brother sin
against me and I forgive him?"
"As many as seven times," Jesus said to
him.
"I do not say to you seven times, but 77
times.
Therefore, the kingdom of heaven may be
compared to a king who wished to settle
accounts with his servants.
When he began to settle, one was brought
to him who owed him 10,000 talents.
And since he could not pay, his master
ordered him to be sold
with his wife and children and all that
he had and payment to be made.
So, the servant fell on his knees
imploring him,
"Have patience with me and I will pay
you everything."
And out of pity for him, the master of
that servant released him and forgave
him the debt.
But when that same servant went out, he
found one of his fellow servants who
owed him 100 denarii. And seizing him,
he began to choke him saying,
"Pay what you owe."
So, his fellow servant fell down and
pleaded with him, "Have patience with me
and I will pay you."
He refused and went and put him in
prison until he should pay the debt.
When his fellow servants saw what had
taken place, they were greatly
distressed and they went and reported to
their master all that had taken place.
Then his master summoned him and said to
him, "You wicked servant, I forgave you
all that debt because you pleaded with
me.
And you should not have had had mercy on
your fellow servant as I have mercy on
you."
on you.
And in anger, his master delivered him
to the jailers until he should pay all
his debt.
So also my heavenly father will do to
every one of you if you do not forgive
your brother from your heart.
Our good and gracious good and gracious
father, we do thank you, Lord, that you
are a good God. We thank you, Lord, for
the blessing we have in this free
country together freely to sing your
praises in this place. And Lord, I pray
as we ask that as we come before your
word this evening, would you just be
with us? Lord, we thank you that all
scripture is God breathed and useful for
teaching, correcting, rebuking, and
training in all righteousness so that
the men of God may be thoroughly
equipped for every good work. We do ask
now, Lord, as we do that, would you
please accomplish your purposes in our
hearts through the preaching of your
word and prayer in Jesus' name. Amen.
>> Well, there was once a story told about
a man who was bitten by a dog.
Which, unfortunately for the man,
was discovered to be rabid.
And after some tests, the man's worst
fears were realized.
He had contracted rabies, an incurable
and terminal disease at that time.
And so, the doctor told the man,
"You know, I suggest that you start
putting your house in order. Maybe write
a will or something."
And at first, the man was shattered. He
was totally devastated.
But he soon gained his composure and
asked the doctor for a pen and some
paper.
An hour passed.
When the doctor returned, he found the
man still writing.
And so, he said to the man,
"Good to see that you're still working
on your will."
To which the man stopped writing, looked
up, and replied to the doctor,
"Will?
What will?
This isn't a will.
This is a list of people I'm going to
bite before I die."
Well, thanks for joining us. We're going
to miss our five-part sermon series on
selected parables of Jesus.
And today, we come to what is a very
practical and relevant parable. Namely,
the parable of the unmerciful or
unforgiving servant.
Now, the reason why I say this is a very
practical and relevant parable is
because this parable is all you guessed
it, forgiveness.
Something that the man bitten by the dog
was clearly lacking.
As As can be seen from the list of
people he wanted to bite and thus get
even with.
And perhaps
just perhaps some of us might also have
a similar kind of list. A mental list of
people who have wronged us or hurt us
and that we might be bitter with and
want to get even with.
And this, unfortunately, isn't uncommon.
Especially in a world, a fallen world
with fallen people, where relational and
interpersonal conflicts are inevitable.
As the old saying goes
to dwell with
to dwell in love with saints above all
that will be glory, but to dwell below
with saints we know, ah, that's another
story.
And friends, given the inevitability of
conflict, the danger, the all too common
danger, is that we harbor these
offenses,
that we allow bitterness to take root in
our hearts,
and that we develop an unforgiving
spirit, one that bears grudges.
That's why I say that this topic is
relevant to us all. Yes, even as
Christians and perhaps especially as
Christians.
For friends, the truth is that while we
as Christians readily proclaim and even
extol the virtue of forgiveness,
our practice may not always match our
words. What's in our heads may not
always translate to our hearts and
hands.
After all, as C.S. Lewis once wisely
remarked,
"Everyone says forgiveness is a lovely
idea until
they have something to forgive."
How true.
And so friends, what I want to see from
today's parable is the simple but
profound truth
that God's forgiven people
forgive people. Like God's forgiven
people forgive people. That I believe is
the main point and takeaway of this
parable, a point that hopefully will
become clear as we make our way through
this story.
Do a pastoral along we'll walk through
the this narrative in three movements.
Three piece again like last week. First,
we look at the problem,
then at the parable, and finally at the
principle. So, let's begin firstly with
the
problem.
There's some problem with this. Okay,
here you go.
All right. Look at verse 21 in your
Bibles.
Then Peter came up and said to him,
"Lord, how often will my brother sin
against me and I forgive him? As many as
seven times?"
Now, here friends, we need to back up
for a moment and consider the context in
which this question arose.
And what we find is that our passage
comes hot on the heels of the preceding
narrative or pericope, namely verses 15
to 20, the famous passage on church
discipline.
And there, if you remember, Jesus Jesus
outlines what we have to do if a
brother, that is a fellow believer, sins
against us. And he outlines three steps
in particular.
First,
since this is a personal
offense, we have to approach the
offending brother privately.
And if he acknowledges his fault and
repents, we have to forgive and
reconcile and the matter is closed.
But,
if the offending brother does not accept
his fault,
we have to proceed to the second stage.
And here, we have to bring in one or two
witnesses for the sake of objectivity.
And if the offending brother is
persuaded by these witnesses and
repents, we have to forgive and
reconcile and the matter again is
closed.
But, if the offending brother is still
adamant and unrepentant after even after
some time has passed, Jesus says they
have to tell it to the church.
After which, if he still refuses to
repent and listen,
we have to treat him as an unbeliever.
That is, we have to excommunicate him.
Even here friends, we need to remember
that the goal of all such church
discipline is not so much punitive as it
is restorative. The goal by God's grace
is restoration, to restore the brother
to Christ.
Now, with this backdrop in mind, I think
Peter's question here in verse 21 makes
sense.
You know, perhaps Peter was thinking
along the lines of this.
I understand if my brother sins against
me, I must confront him.
I also know that if he listens and
repents for the first time, I must
forgive him.
But what if he offends me again and
again and again?
And yet repents again and again and
again.
How many times should I forgive him?
As many as seven times?
Now, if you think about it, this is a
fair question on Peter's part.
You know, he wanted to know what to do
in the event that a brother sins against
him repeatedly and yet repents.
And what's amazing here is that Peter
does not only ask the question, but he
also gives an answer, a very generous
and magnanimous answer.
One that would have even even floored
even the most pious of Jews.
For instance, you see, the rabbis of
Jesus' day recommended, based on the
reading, or should I say a misreading,
of texts such as Amos 1 and 2 about God
revoking punishment for three offenses
but not four, these rabbis, they
recommend limiting forgiveness to three
times.
So, for example, in the tractate Yoma,
Rabbi Jose ben Judah had laid on this
rule. He said this,
"If a brother sins against you once,
forgive him.
A second time,
A third time,
forgive him. But a fourth time, do not
forgive him."
Well, Peter, perhaps aware of this, as
well as the countercultural ways of
Jesus' kingdom, he not only doubles the
number, but adds one to it for effect.
"As many as seven times?" he asks.
Now, first of all, one wonders what was
going on in Peter's mind at this point.
You know, perhaps he's uh hoping or
maybe even uh expecting to hear from
Jesus,
"Well done. Good on you, Peter. You are
a fast learner. You have learned the
ways of the kingdom. Yes, we have to
forgive not just three times like the
those rabbis, but we have to forgive 7
times.
But friends, that's not what Jesus says,
does he?
Notice what Jesus says in verse 22.
He says
to him, "I I do not say to you seven
times, but 77
times."
And did you catch that? Not seven times,
the biblical number that signifies
completeness or perfection, but 77
times.
Now, the Greek here is actually quite
ambiguous.
But the phrase could mean, as the ESV
renders it, 77 times,
or it could mean, as the LSB translates
it, seven times 70 times seven. Which if
if taken literally would amount to a
whopping not 490 times.
But friends, whatever way you translate
it, the point is that Jesus is not here
prescribing a limit to the number of
times we have to forgive, whether 77 or
490.
No, his point is that there should be no
limit whatsoever to our extension of
forgiveness to those who repent.
Simply put, this is a call for a
boundless and limitless forgiveness.
Now, I'm not sure about you, friends,
but it may seem difficult,
radical, and perhaps even humanly
impossible. And indeed, it is.
Which is why Jesus follows this up with
a parable. Look at verse 23 with me in
your Bible.
Jesus begins.
Therefore, the kingdom of heaven may be
compared to a king who wished to settle
accounts with his servants.
Right. So, Jesus here he paints the
setting or backdrop, if you will, of the
parable.
It has to do with a king who wanted to
settle accounts with his servants. Which
by the way may, in this context,
probably refer to high-ranking officials
in a huge colonial empire.
And having painted the context, the back
the backdrop, Jesus next paints three
portraits as he walks through the scenes
of this parable.
First, a portrait of a merciful master.
Then, a portrait of an unmerciful
servant. And finally, a portrait of an
incensed master. We'll take each of
these in turn.
So, first
the portrait of a merciful master. Look
at verse 24.
When he, that is the king, began to
settle, one was brought to him who owed
him 10,000
talents, right? 10,000 talents.
Now, friends, if you're like me, you're
probably thinking over here, what in the
world is a talent?
How much exactly is 10,000 talents? How
much are we talking about here?
Well, scholars agree that one talent
equaled 600 denarii.
And a denarius, well, it's simply a
day's wage for a common laborer.
And if you do the math, or maybe look
down in your footnotes in your Bible,
you realize that one talent amounts to
about 20 years of wages for a common
laborer. 20 years, that's a lot.
Now, think with me for a moment.
If one talent equals 20 years
wages,
how many years wages would 10,000
talents
amount to?
Answer, a whopping 200,000
years' worth of wages, right? 200,000.
That's just crazy. That's a lot. Right,
we're talking somewhere along the lines
of millions, if not billions, of
dollars. It's an astronomical and indeed
an incalculable amount.
And that's precisely the point. Now,
Jesus wants to highlight over here, he
wants to accentuate in a drastic fashion
the immeasurable amount of debt that
this servant owed.
Simply put, it was an unpayable debt.
There's no way, no way whatsoever, that
this servant would be able to pay back
this debt.
Now, this, by the way, if you think
about it, is analogous to the debt that
we as sinners owe before an infinitely
holy God.
Right, that I believe is the parallel
that Jesus wants Peter and us to draw
here.
God is the king and we are the servant
in this parable.
And because of our sins, we owe him an
astronomical and indeed an incalculable
amount of debt, one that we could never,
ever repay, not even in a million years.
For friends, the fact is that just one
sin, just one, is enough to condemn us
to hell for all eternity.
And we've all sinned and fallen short of
the glory of God.
So, we in many ways are like the servant
in this parable.
Hopeless, helpless, and hapless with a
mountain of debt before us.
Let's continue verse 25.
Oops.
Yep, verse 25. And since he could not
pay, his master ordered him to be sold
with his wife and children and all he
had in payment to be made.
To which the the servant in verse 26
falls on his knees, implores the king
saying, "Have patience with me and I
will pay you back everything."
Now here friends, we can't help but see
on the one hand the appropriateness of
this response and on the other hand the
absurdity of this response.
First, given the plight that he's in,
the servant does the only thing that is
appropriate, namely to beg for the
king's mercy.
However, inherently in the servant's
response is also an absurdity.
Did you notice it? Look at what he says
again.
He says, "Have patience with me." And
not this,
"I will pay you
everything."
Now we've just told we've just been told
how much he owes. 10,000 talents, or if
you like, a 200,000 year wage.
There's no way, right, no way whatsoever
that this guy is going to pay back what
he owes.
So, what he says here is either born out
of desperation, if not deception.
And this friends, by the way, if you
think about it,
it reveals to us the utter futility of
trying to earn our salvation or to do
penance in endeavor to atone for our
sins. It's impossible. It's a fool's
errand. It's a dead end street. But
there's no way that we can ever earn our
salvation or repay the debt that we owe
to God for our sins.
But somehow, in our hubris and pride, we
humans think that we are able to do
that. That is, to make up for our sins,
our many sins.
Well, how would the master respond?
Well, verse 27.
And out of pity for him, the master of
that servant released him and forgave
him the debt. All right, did you get
that? This is amazing. Just amazing.
Well, the master, we are told, he pitied
the servant. He had compassion
for the servant. And he did the
unthinkable.
He not only released the servant, but he
also forgives him the debt, the enormous
debt.
And this, of course, at great cost to
himself. After all, it's his money, and
so he has to absorb the cost, the great
cost.
And brothers and sisters, if this is not
amazing grace, I do not know what is.
And this again, friends, is a picture,
one intended, I believe, by Jesus, of
the grace, the amazing grace that God
has shown to us in Christ, in forgiving
us the mountain of debt that we owe him
for our sins, our many sins.
But friends,
just when we expect the story to end,
Jesus continues with the second scene.
And here he paints for us the portrait
of an an unmerciful servant. Look at
verse 20 to 30, 28 to 30.
He says,
"But when that same servant went out, he
found one of his fellow servants who
owed him 100 denarii." Now, remember
here over here, a denarius, as mentioned
earlier, is a day's wage for a common
laborer.
So, 100 denarii, if you do the math, is
approximately around 3 to 4 months'
worth of wages.
Now, think about it for a moment. This
is not a small or trivial amount. It's
not insignificant or insubstantial. All
right, just imagine not being paid your
wages for 3 or 4 months. That's quite a
lot of money.
And this, remember, is what this servant
owed his fellow servant.
And so what does this servant do?
Well, verse 28 tells us that he seized
him and began to choke him saying, "Pay
back what you owe." And verse 29,
"So his fellow servant fell down and
pleaded with him, 'Have patience with me
and I will pay you.'"
Now here friends, I think we're meant to
feel a sense of déjà vu.
We get a flashback of sorts of what has
happened earlier in the previous scene.
In fact, the wording is deliberately
almost the same.
Verse 26, "Have patience with me and I
will pay you back everything."
Verse 29, "Have patience with me and I
will
pay you."
And as readers, we're meant to draw the
connection over here.
This second servant, being in a similar
plight to that of the first servant, he
begged for mercy.
He, as the first servant had done
earlier, he asked for time and this so
that he can repay the debt.
So the exact same thing is being played
out here.
And the big question in our minds is
this,
what will this servant, the servant who
had just been forgiven an enormous debt
by the king, do?
You know, will he likewise extend the
mercy that he had received to his fellow
servant, albeit with a much smaller sum?
Well, verse 28 verse 32 gives us the
answer.
It says, "He refused and went and put
him in prison until he should pay the
debt."
And here brothers and sisters, we're
meant to feel a sense of holy
indignation rising in our hearts. We're
meant to see the discrepancy between how
the king treated this servant and how
this servant treated his fellow servant.
And this is further accentuated when we
consider the num- the amounts owed. Now,
the first servant, if you remember, owed
10,000 talents. That's about 60 million
denarii.
A debt that as we saw was impossible to
repay.
But his fellow servant owed how much?
A hundred denarii. That is that as we
saw was about three to four months worth
of wages. A debt that that like unlike
the previous one is certainly possible
to repay.
And so there there ought to be a
cognitive dissonance developing within
us. Something just isn't right here.
And you're right to feel this way.
For we expect when we the disobedient
who had tested first hand the gracious
benevolence of the king in forgiving him
his insurmountable debt, they should
likewise as well extend mercy to his
fellow servant and forgive him of his
significantly smaller debt.
Like that after all is the only logical
thing to do.
But he doesn't.
I mean this servant in spite of
receiving abundant grace from the king,
he hardened his heart against the plight
of his fellow slave, locked him up in
jail and demanded payment. He demanded
that justice be done.
And this brings us to the third scene of
the parable. And here Jesus paints for
us a very different portrait from that
of the first.
He paints for us a portrait of an
incensed king.
Look at verse 31.
When his fellow servants saw what had
taken place, they noted the servant's
treatment of his fellow slave, they were
greatly distressed.
And why?
Well, because they like us know that
something isn't right here. They see the
injustice and discrepancy in what's
going on.
And so they went and reported to their
master all that had taken place.
And what does the master do? Well,
verses 32 and 33.
Then his master summoned him and said to
him, "You wicked servant."
Right so over here the master is
exposing this servant's character. He's
wicked, he has an evil heart as can be
seen in his actions.
And the master continues.
"I forgave you all that debt because you
pleaded with me. And should you not have
had mercy on your fellow servant as I
had mercy on you?"
So friends, the logic is clear.
Those who had received mercy
should show mercy.
And the Greek word underlying the word
should here is emphatic. Right, it's the
word day,
a word that implies necessity or
obligation.
In other words, this is not an option
but an obligation. It's a requirement.
Right, there's an oughtness to this.
Those who have received mercy should or
are expected are expected to show mercy
to others.
Something that this servant quite
clearly hasn't done. He did not extend
the grace that he received from the king
to his fellow servant and that for a
significantly smaller amount. Think of
that.
And so what does the master do?
Well, verse 34.
And in in his anger, his master
delivered him over to the jailers until
he should repay all his debt.
And if you stop over here, we can't help
but notice the difference in demeanor of
the king.
Right, whereas previously in verse 27,
the king was moved with compassion when
the servant pleaded with him,
here in verse 35, the king was moved
with indignation when he heard what the
servant had done.
And the reason for the king's anger,
similar to ours, is because of the
discrepancy and the injustice that had
taken place.
This servant who had received the
extraordinary mercy from the king when
he fell on his knees and begged him
ought to have shown the same mercy to
his fellow servant when he likewise fell
on his knees and begged him.
But he did not do that.
And so the king revokes his earlier
decision and he metes out justice on
this wicked servant. Verse 34.
He delivered him to the jailers and note
this,
until
he should pay not some but all his debt.
Now friends, if you stop and think for a
moment over here,
this is in this in fact a life sentence.
For this debt, this incalculable debt as
we saw was simply unpayable.
Now friends, while some scholars debate
what this verse implies, I think it's
pretty clear that due to the unpayable
nature of the debt, that the
imprisonment over here refers not
ultimately to a temporal punishment, but
rather an eternal punishment, namely
hell. Right, that's what's at stake over
here.
So that's the parable that Jesus tells
in answer to Peter's question about
forgiveness.
And having told the parable, Jesus
concludes with a principle.
And it's an alarming and sobering one.
Look at the principle.
Verse 35.
Jesus concludes the parable by saying,
"So also my heavenly Father will do to
everyone of you if you do not forgive
your brother and notice this, from your
heart." All right, from your heart.
Now, what does Jesus mean by this?
Well, I think it simply means that our
forgiveness of others, especially those
who repent, must be sincere and not
hypocritical.
That is, we can't just mouth the words,
"I forgive you." without meaning it from
the bottom of our hearts.
Now, just to be clear, friends,
this doesn't mean that we forget or even
excuse what had happened.
It doesn't mean that there are no
consequences for sin, legal or
otherwise.
And it doesn't mean that our
relationship with that person has to go
back as per normal, so to speak.
But what it does mean is this.
It means that we do not hold that sin
against the repentant offender.
That we let go of any bitterness or
resentment.
And that we lay venge- vengeance aside
and desire the good of the one who hurt
us.
That's what forgiveness from the heart
means.
Now, my brothers and sisters,
that said, what Jesus says here in this
verse, as mentioned, is sobering,
utterly sobering. And we should not and
indeed dare not water down what Jesus
says over here as some have tried to do.
I think what Jesus says is plain.
And just as the king threw the
unmerciful and unforgiving servant into
jail until he could repay his debt,
which is an impossibility,
so too will God do to everyone of us if
we do not forgive our brother from our
heart.
And this, as we said earlier, is not a
reference to some temporal punishment in
this life and certainly not purgatory,
but a reference to eternal punishment,
hell, in the life to come. Right, that's
what we're talking about here.
And thus, we do well as God's people to
take heed and ensure that we that no
root of bitterness springs within our
hearts, and that we do not harbor the
sin of unforgiveness in our hearts.
For nothing less than eternity is at
stake over here.
Now, this text, of course, raises some
questions.
For one thing,
what about the security of believers?
Did not Jesus say that he will lose he
will lose none of those he saves?
Now, how then do we reconcile this verse
with all the passages that highlight the
eternal security of believers?
For another thing,
does this then mean that Jesus is here
teaching a form of salvation by works,
or more specifically, salvation by
forgiveness?
After all, it seems that God's
forgiveness of us is contingent upon our
forgiveness of others.
Now, friends, these are good and
legitimate questions. And it shows that
we are thinking biblically when we raise
questions such as this.
So, how should we answer these
questions?
Well, what we understand is that yes,
while it's true that that that there is
an yes, inextricable link between our
forgiveness of others and God's
forgiveness of us,
it doesn't follow that we are saved by
means of our forgiving of others, or
even that our salvation can be lost or
revoked.
But it's a non sequitur, so to speak.
So, to untangle the apparent conundrum,
we need to remember the central and
unshakeable truth of the Christian
faith. And it is this:
We are saved by grace alone, through
faith alone, in Christ alone, and all of
this to the glory of God alone.
And that's what we must hold to and
affirm based on the testimony of
scripture alone.
But friends,
at the same time, scripture also
teaches, as the reformers tell us to,
famously, yes, we are saved by faith
alone,
but the faith that saves is what?
Never
alone.
And the reason for this is because when
God saves us, he regenerates us. That
is, he gives us a new heart and a new
nature. We are a new creation in Christ.
Now, this, of course, friends, doesn't
mean that as Christians, we are sinless
or that we don't struggle with sin.
I will all know from scripture and from
experience as well that we still do sin
and we still do struggle with sin.
But the difference is that with this new
nature, we increasingly and inevitably
reflect the character of Christ in our
lives, however imperfectly that may be
in this life.
And part of the character of Christ is
that of a disposition, an inclination,
if you will, to forgive.
Right, but to forgive as Christ has
forgiven us.
Now, let me just be clear over here.
This doesn't mean that forgiveness will
always come quickly or even easily.
It doesn't. Especially when we have been
deeply offended or hurt by others.
And so, we don't want to downplay that.
But having said that, I think it's also
true that as Christians, because of
being made new, we have an innate desire
to obey God and to do his will. Yes,
even though it may be difficult, and
yes, even though we may at times resist
his will.
So, putting all of this together, we can
say that our forgiveness of those who
repent is an evidence that we have been
forgiven by God. Right, the former is
the fruit and the latter is the root, if
you will.
And friends, what's scary over here?
The scary thing about verse 35
is not so much that we can lose our
salvation, because scripture clearly
teaches otherwise.
But that we, by our persistent and
ongoing unforgiveness, even to those who
repent, may prove ourselves to be mere
professors rather than possessors of the
faith. Right, we show that the life of
Christ is not in us, that we are not
true Christians.
And so, friends, this is a warning. It's
a sobering wake-up call.
For the truth is that God's forgiven
people forgive people.
And if you think about it, it makes
sense.
As God has As Jesus has shown in shown
us in this parable, we who have been
forgiven an incalculable and
insurmountable amount of debt like the
servant did, ought to likewise forgive
the debts of others, which in comparison
to our sin against an infinitely holy
God is minuscule and tiny.
So, if God has forgiven us our many sins
and trespasses against him,
it only makes sense that we should
forgive others who have sinned against
us and repented.
That, brothers and sisters, is the
simple but profound point of this
parable. God's forgiven people forgive
people.
Something simple to understand but hard
to do.
So, friends, if you struggle with
forgiveness even though the offending
party has repented,
I'm going to catch all of us here.
Take a moment, maybe, you know,
devotions this evening or maybe tomorrow
morning,
take a moment to pause, reflect, and
meditate upon the forgiveness that we
have in Christ.
Or more specifically,
take a moment to prayerfully reflect
upon the extent and magnitude of our
debt before a a holy and just God. How
much God cannot stand sin and how much
our sin is an affront to a God whose
eyes are too pure to look on evil.
Then, having done that,
take a moment to prayerfully reflect
upon the cost, the infinite cost to God
in procuring our salvation and forgiving
us this debt, our sins.
For brothers and sisters,
it did not cost God millions or billions
of dollars to redeem us, as amazing as
that is,
but it cost God nothing less than the
blood of his son, our Lord and Savior
Jesus Christ, to redeem us and forgive
us our sins.
And friends, when we do that,
when we realize the vast extent of our
guilt and the immense cost to God in
procuring our salvation,
how can we, who have been forgiven so
infinite a debt, withhold forgiveness
from others who have sinned in much
lesser ways against us and yet have
repented?
It's unthinkable as it is impossible.
As that should be with the new nature
that we've been given in Christ.
So, friends, as we close for today,
let me just ask
as a practical takeaway,
are there people in your life that you
have yet to forgive because of some past
hurt, misunderstanding, or whatever, but
know that you need to forgive?
If so, would you pray and ask for the
Lord's help,
not only to heal your wounds,
but also for his power to forgive?
Or maybe even seek some counseling help
if need be.
May we, friends, as God's forgiven
people,
forgive
people.
And here, friends, I think it's a good
time to transit over to communion. This
is the third Sunday of the of the week
of the month. So, it's time of communion
right now. And communion, the Lord's
Supper, as we know, is a time in which
we as Christians pause to remember
specifically the person and work of
Christ. That is, who Jesus is and what
he accomplished on the cross in our
place and for our sins.
As I mentioned earlier, we are in many
ways like the servant in this parable
who owed an incalculable and
insurmountable amount of debt.
And nothing we can do can ever repay the
debt that we owe to God because of our
sins.
For none of us, being inherently sinful,
can ever atone for our sins, let alone
the sins of others.
But, friends, the great news, the
glorious news, as we saw, was that when
the servant begged for mercy from the
king,
he surprisingly got mercy.
Now, it's not what he deserved, but he
got it anyway.
The king, at great cost to himself, he
forgave him all his debt.
And this, friends, is a picture, a
glorious picture, of the grace and mercy
that God has shown to us in Christ.
For even while we were still sinners,
the Bible tells us, God in this love, he
sent his only son to die for the sins of
people. And he paid their debt, and this
so that those who believe may be
forgiven and reconciled to a holy God.
And that's what we as God's forgiven
forgiven people, those of us who are
flying to Christ for salvation are
remembering and celebrating each time we
come for communion.
We are celebrating his wonderful work of
grace in forgiving us our debt. And this
by means of his atonement on the cross
in our place and for our sins.
Oh Father God,
what grace, what infinite grace this is.
That you the holy one should give of
your one and only son, our Lord and
Savior Jesus Christ, to not only come as
a man, as amazing as that is, but also
to die on the cross. And this in our
place
and for our sins.
Indeed, we thank you, Lord, that the
elements that we just partook, the bread
and the cup, they remind us of the
truth, the glorious truth, that Jesus
died to pay a debt that he did not owe
because he owed a debt that we could
never pay.
And as a people forgiven by your grace,
help us, too, likewise to extend
forgiveness to those who have hurt us,
however deeply, and by your grace have
repented.
Grant us, oh Lord,
the grace to do just that. Namely, to
forgive as Christ has forgiven us. And
this, so that we may reflect your
character, your love, and that we may
glorify your name. We ask these in
Jesus' name. Amen.